<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Scratchings]]></title>
  <link href="http://shanel.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shanel.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-09T17:38:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://shanel.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shane Liebling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Questions]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/06/09/questions/"/>
<updated>2013-06-09T11:07:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/06/09/questions</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I live in a big city. Every day people stand on the streets begging for money. Seeing people beg upsets me. I become physically ill. It also makes me question my personal values and those imposed upon me by society.</p>

<p>Why does society leave these people with no alternative except begging for money? Why am I uncomfortable having any kind of interaction with them beyond that of a financial transaction? (It is a transaction. The receipt for which would include Assuagement of Purchaser&rsquo;s Guilt, Purchaser&rsquo;s Experience of Seller&rsquo;s Gratitude, and Purchaser&rsquo;s Feeling of Having Helped A Fellow Human Being.)</p>

<p>What prevents me from starting a conversation with this person? Would they accept a conversation as an alternative to a financial transaction? Would they use the conversation to increase the likelihood of the financial transaction occurring?</p>

<p>Why are we taught as children never to talk to strangers? Why is a stranger more dangerous than someone we know?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Why do we continue to believe this as adults? Why doesn&rsquo;t this rule apply when money is involved? (People begging on the street have to talk to strangers because the more people they ask the more chances they will receive money. Similarly when strangers enter a business the employees must talk with them so as to increase the likelihood of their becoming paying customers.)<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>What troubles me most about this situation is the discrepancy in power. The person with the money is in a position of power over the person without the money. They get to decide whether the other person will have to interact with them or not. The customer is always right. This is because the customer has the money and you (or the business you work for) want the money. I hate this. I see abusive patrons of retail or food places lambast the people who work there. The workers believe they have to put up with it, for fear of losing their job. Why can&rsquo;t the situation be one where if the patron gives the worker shit, the worker can give them shit back and tell them to leave? If the patron didn&rsquo;t like the meal, they don&rsquo;t have to pay for it and they are welcome to leave.</p>

<p>Outside of situations where it is assumed strangers will talk to you (like bars), when are we comfortable with this happening? Does it require a common experience? Walking down the street I see someone wearing a shirt from the college I attended. I can talk to them once I explain we went to the same school. If I and another passenger on the subway see something outrageous happen, we can talk about it and other such experiences.</p>

<p>Religious beliefs appear to have a similar effect. If a stranger shows up at a house of worship, it is assumed they are a member of the faith. They will be spoken to and invited to be a member of the local group. All of this happens based on an assumption of shared beliefs.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>Why can&rsquo;t our common experience be the fact that we are human beings? We have all grown up and gone through similar experiences. We might not have experienced them together, but we both have been through those experiences before. We&rsquo;ve all been through breakups.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> We&rsquo;ve all been scared before. We&rsquo;ve all been happy before.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>Why does seeing this person in need affect me so deeply? Am I particularly empathetic? Is it because in the past I have been in dire financial straits and have had to beg family members for money? (ie a common experience) Is it because I worry I might be in that place once again in the future?</p>

<p>Who benefits from the continuing distance between myself and this other person? I can&rsquo;t see how either I or the other person benefit (other than financially, in which case the benefit is only temporary and one-sided).<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> Who benefits from people who have something in common feeling an unbridgeable gap between them? Who benefits when people see others begging and feel that at any moment they could be in that other person&rsquo;s shoes? Who benefits when we fear the other?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Stranger danger! IIRC statistics show a child is more likely to be abducted or abused by someone they know than by someone they don&rsquo;t.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>There is discomfort anytime money is involved with family or friends, though. An anecdote: I grew up playing boardgames with my friends, it was one of the main ways we spent time together. I have recently found there is a game store in my city where you can pay the employees to play board games with you. This feels very wrong to me.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Many religions say to welcome and take care of the stranger. I think most translate this to mean &ldquo;a member of the religion you have not yet met,&rdquo; not just any stranger.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Relationships are something most people have experienced. Yet they are one of the things they tend to be the most guarded about. Is that because they are seen as only between the person and the other member of the relationship? Thus making discussion about them with anyone else something that goes against the taboo of talking to strangers? (ie the other member of the relationship does not know the stranger, thus cannot give their permission to talk about them) That said, people will talk to friends about the relationship &ndash; people who already have experience or connection to the other party. Or they will talk to their therapist &ndash; someone they pay to talk to.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Maybe this is why people read. They find this other person (the author or the character) who has done or felt things like the reader has. They (at least in their minds) have this friend to talk to for a short span of time, who seems to have something in common with them.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>The Free Hugs people seem to prove the opposite is true. When two people who have nothing in common beyond their own willingness to hug another person come together, both of their lives are improved.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/06/09/questions/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Adrift]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/26/adrift/"/>
<updated>2013-05-26T20:55:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/26/adrift</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I returned from SF recently. I went to college in the Bay Area and my company&rsquo;s headquarters is there as well. Most of my college friends still live there. I left the Bay Area six years ago for New York.</p>

<p>I assumed when I moved here that either I would get closer with friends from work or I would find new friends. Six years later, neither of these things have really occurred, or if they have they are now strained by changes in people&rsquo;s lives. In the back of my mind though, I saw myself as still part of that community of friends. I&rsquo;m not so sure anymore.</p>

<p>Over those six years those friends have visited NYC individually. As they have I have heard about their lives and through them the lives of other friends. I understood in a theoretically that they were a community and deeply involved in one another&rsquo;s lives, but never saw it explicitly. This gave my mind the chance to continue its belief that I could still be part of that community.</p>

<p>Visiting these friends in SF though, I feel that possibility slipping away. I see now that they have moved on with their lives &ndash; as a group. They have moved on without my being a part of that group. A number of them will be getting married soon, I wonder if I will be invited. Where in the past dinners with them would go on for hours, full of conversation. Now conversation dries up quickly because I am not a part of their world and thus don&rsquo;t know the people they know who they normally would talk about.</p>

<p>I have another friend who had moved to NYC from the Bay Area. She was here a year or two when she had a major health incident. She has since moved back to the Bay Area because that is where all her friends were, where her support network was. I saw her when I was out there and she said she might have been able to stay in NYC if she had found a partner out here, someone to ground her. I got lucky and found a partner out here, but if I had not I might have done the same as she did.</p>

<p>A partner though does not a community make. I have been able to somewhat become a part of my partner&rsquo;s friend group, but that doesn&rsquo;t fill the void of real friends. If anything it might have been a crutch I thought I could lean on. A crutch isn&rsquo;t meant to be used indefinitely.</p>

<p>Maybe it comes down to shared experiences. In college you meet people and stay with them to develop a history of shared experiences together. It is from this foundation that your future community can be formed. When you are unmoored from that foundation you won&rsquo;t be grounded in another community until you have had shared experiences with those other people.</p>

<p>I am going to have to find that group of people and put in the time and effort to have those shared experiences.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/26/adrift/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycles]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/12/cycles/"/>
<updated>2013-05-12T18:16:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/12/cycles</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We recently got a puppy. She doesn&rsquo;t let us sleep as much as we used to. I tend to be the one who wakes up with her early in the morning. A few weeks ago I slept poorly and was in a foul mood in the morning. When the puppy was getting into something she shouldn&rsquo;t I swatted her away. Unfortunately I did so in anger and with strength. I literally shoved her a few inches in the air and into the nearby wall.</p>

<p>She was wary of me for the rest of the morning. I felt horrible. I tried to &ldquo;make it up to her&rdquo; by giving her treats, feeding her breakfast immediately, etc. I felt sick the rest of the morning. This wasn&rsquo;t the type of person I was. I didn&rsquo;t hurt dogs.</p>

<p>As someone who was the victim of violence a lot as a child (mostly bullying) I tend to be passive. I don&rsquo;t like violence and go out of my way not to be aggressive. As I have grown older though and been tired and frustrated and exasperated more times in my life, I have come to realize that the possibility of aggression and violence is there inside me.</p>

<p>My mother was a believer in spanking. For one reason or another she felt it had a place in parenting. I assume this was because she was spanked as a child as well. I am sure she truly thought that I &ldquo;learned a lesson&rdquo; when she spanked me, telling me all the while what lesson I should be learning. What I learned was to fear my mother. I don&rsquo;t think children (and certainly not dogs) learn from the trauma of violence. Your mind is focused on making the pain stop, or just surviving it. <em>Maybe</em> afterward you try to use logic to figure out what you should have done differently, but the likelihood is you are too young and immature to remember that lesson in the future. Young children (like dogs) do many things because they are swept up by emotions and feelings and ideas, not because they have performed some sort of calculus weighing the possible outcomes and coming to a logical decision about the next action.</p>

<p>Although spanking (or beating) is certainly counter-productive for children learning anything useful, it is a release for the parent. It allows them to vent their frustration and tiredness directly on the cause of those things. It is one of the few times that society fully allows them to become violent and inflict pain and suffering on another human being without fear of legal consequences. So in the heat of the moment, a parent will do what feels good to them, even if they are saying &ldquo;this is going to hurt me more than it is going to hurt you&rdquo; as they do so.</p>

<p>In actuality I think there is a second thing children learn when they are spanked, beyond the fact that they should fear their parents, they learn that it is okay to hurt their children. A primal lesson is ensconced in their brain and some day in the future when they have a child and they are tired and exasperated and frustrated they will make use of that lesson. They will teach their child the same lessons they learned at the hands of their parents. The same one their child will teach their child.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/12/cycles/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Recipes]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/05/recipes/"/>
<updated>2013-05-05T19:39:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/05/recipes</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My brother-in-law is an intuitive cook. He rarely makes use of recipes. I on the other hand rely on recipes for my cooking. I may have cooked something ten times, but I always cook it after reviewing the recipe. I might make minor changes here and there based on missing ingredients, but I still need the recipe there as a guide. The recipe has been tried and tested and published based on its previous successes. If something doesn&rsquo;t taste good, but you followed the recipe, you can blame the recipe, not the cook.</p>

<p>Although undiagnosed, my mother likely had either borderline or narcissistic personality disorder. What this meant in practical terms was that she was moody and almost anything could set her off. She could be loving one moment, and then the next be screaming at you, set off by some minor thing you might have done. The common refrain is &ldquo;it&rsquo;s like walking on eggshells around them.&rdquo;</p>

<p>As a child I spent a lot of time with my mother. She was a stay-at-home-mom until I was in middle school. That meant I needed to figure out what would set her off and what wouldn&rsquo;t. The logic I think I eventually developed was a reversal on that old line &ldquo;it&rsquo;s easier to ask for forgiveness than it is to ask for permission.&rdquo; In my case it turned into, &ldquo;it&rsquo;s easier to ask permission than to receive forgiveness.&rdquo; I think my child-logic was, if she knows what I am doing, or I do what she tells me to, then she can&rsquo;t possibly get upset at the outcome.</p>

<p>A corollary to this rule was don&rsquo;t upset anyone, and if you did, figure out how and never do it again. That was my modus operandi in elementary school. Other than doing well in my classes I tried to not make myself stand out. Sadly, this rarely worked. I was a target for bullies and was regularly beaten up. I would always, afterwards, try and figure out what it was that I had done to make them want to beat me up. I came up with theories and would implement the conclusions of those theories, and it would never help. (Behaviorists would probably see this as the development of superstitions &ndash; ie the application of logic to something illogical.)</p>

<p>Eventually I filled the role of the class whipping boy so well that even other kids low in the pecking order started picking on me. After this went on for long enough I finally snapped and fought back. Bad idea. Especially because I did this in front of a teacher. I was almost suspended. The lesson I learned? Don&rsquo;t fight back, don&rsquo;t step out of your role, or something even worse than what you are suffering might come down on you.</p>

<p>This mentality made its presence known in my first marriage as well. I would ask my wife permission to go hang out with friends for an evening instead of just telling her I was going out with friends. This wasn&rsquo;t because she demanded it (she always said yes) but that I wasn&rsquo;t willing to be wrong and possibly upset her. This unwillingness to stray from the norm and try something new was definitely a contributing factor to the failure of that marriage.</p>

<p>How do you go against that internalized mindset of &ldquo;don&rsquo;t rock the boat or there will be hell to pay?&rdquo; I think there are two things that can allow you to do this. One is determining that the consequences actually aren&rsquo;t as dire as you feel they are. The other is with the support of people who genuinely care about you and your well being. If you know there are people there who will catch you, it is much easier to let yourself do something where you might fall.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/05/05/recipes/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Absence]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/28/absence/"/>
<updated>2013-04-28T21:20:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/28/absence</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You walk down the stairs past the bedroom window. It is dark and quiet. You open the gate and close it quietly behind you. You unlock the door and open it. She isn&rsquo;t sitting on the couch. You&rsquo;re about to call out her name and say that you are home, then you remember why she isn&rsquo;t there and you stay quiet. The thing in your gut twists.</p>

<p>You hear nothing. You are so used to hearing the television on in the bedroom where she spent so much of her time, but you hear nothing. You&rsquo;ve come home to a silent apartment before, when she was out of town on business, or visiting her parents. That silence you never minded, possibly even enjoyed. This silence is different. That silence had an end. Knowing there was an end to it you didn&rsquo;t mind it. Maybe you didn&rsquo;t even notice it. This silence has no end. This silence makes you focus on it and the reason for it. It makes you think about that thing you don&rsquo;t want to think about. The thing in your gut struggles to free itself. You push it back down.</p>

<p>You do the things you do in an evening. You eat. You read. You go to the bedroom. You don&rsquo;t want to go to the bedroom, but you go anyway.</p>

<p>You see the bed. Its just as you left it in the morning. There are fewer clothes strewn about the floor than there should be. There&rsquo;s a pillow missing.</p>

<p>You change into your pajamas and go to the bathroom. There&rsquo;s a toothbrush missing. There&rsquo;s three bottles of hair product missing from the shower. You wash your hands. You go to wash under your wedding band, but it isn&rsquo;t there. There&rsquo;s just your finger, slightly white and indented.</p>

<p>You go back to the bedroom, set your alarm, get in bed and turn out the light.
You have an urge to turn over and say something. You have said this thing almost every night for the last three years. The words meant less recently than they did in the past, but you said them anyway. Instead you say nothing. You stay on your side. You could stretch out, but you don&rsquo;t. You don&rsquo;t roll over, throughout the night if you feel the urge to roll over, you stifle it.</p>

<p>You sleep sounder than you have in the past, but when you wake up, you forget for a moment, and you look over, you look over like you have for at least a thousand mornings in your life. You see the sheets covering a depression in the mattress, a space that will never again be perfectly filled.</p>

<p>The thing in your gut makes it&rsquo;s move. It wants out. It starts as a wail and gets louder, then breaks up into the regular beat of sobbing. You find a pillow and stuff your face into it, momentarily worried someone will hear you. It just keeps going, or so it seems. Eventually it stops. You pull your head from the pillow and look at the ghost face left by your tears. You turn the pillow over and find something to wipe your eyes with.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/28/absence/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Cooking]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/21/cooking/"/>
<updated>2013-04-21T16:28:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/21/cooking</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The counters are wiped down and the main course is in the oven. There is a break in the action and I wonder what it is that drives me to cook with such ferocity and passion. Other than sex there are few more intimate things you can do for another person beyond cooking and eating with them. Something you prepared is going to be consumed by them &ndash; the level of trust to allow that to happen is, if you think about it, extraordinary.</p>

<p>Maybe that is one reason I feel so drawn to cooking for those I care about. I doubt I could be a professional chef, because although I care about the craft I care more about the action itself and its purpose: that of showing my love and affection for others.</p>

<p>Telling people how much I care about them isn&rsquo;t something I do as often as I should. Over time I have learned the importance of such words and have trained myself to be better about it in my most intimate of relationships, but it is still a struggle for me beyond that realm. My natural tendency is to show people I care through my actions, by going out with them and buying them drinks, spending time talking to them , visiting them when I am in town, and of course, cooking for them.</p>

<p>I look over at the clock on the oven: a little more than two hours until my father and his fiancee arrive. They have been in town for the last week and although we have dined with them twice during that time this is the first time I have cooked for them.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think of my mother all that often. We had a difficult relationship from high school onward. On her side she had a heart attack just before I went to high school after which she intentionally pushed me away emotionally, worried she might die at any moment and I would be crushed. On my side I was a normal teenager who ended up moving away for college and getting a girlfriend who would eventually become my first wife. Her family lived near where we went to school so we spent more time with them than we did with my parents. The distance in time and space never sat well with my mother. Once I moved away for college, holidays like Thanksgiving and Christmas Eve became much more important to her. She would be livid if we decided to participate in the holidays with my in-laws instead of with her.</p>

<p>Eventually I separated from my first wife but around the same time my mother was diagnosed with breast cancer. She died less than a year later. The effort she had started in high school had been a success: I was much less distraught when it happened than I might have been. Of course, it also means I never really got to know her as an adult, other than as an adversary of sorts who I think eventually come to regret her choice to push me away, so much so that she raged at my desire to stay away.</p>

<p>Before middle school, when she went back to work, I remember my mother always having cooked dinner for my father and I. It was simple fare but it filled us and fueled my growth. I assume my mother learned to cook from her mother who had grown up in the Great Depression. As such, much of what was served at home was inexpensive types of fish (like Orange Roughy) and meat (fried chicken gizzards and hearts).</p>

<p>My mother never taught me to cook, I taught myself and learned a bit from my first wife&rsquo;s step-father. I cook from recipes for the most part, only really cooking the most basic things intuitively, like omelets and meatballs.</p>

<p>As I grow older I think more and more about how I became the person I am. I wonder how much I learned to express my love for others through cooking from my mother. Was that the way she expressed her love? Was that the reason why when all other avenues of communication had broken down she so desperately wanted me to come to the holidays when she would cook? Was she trying to tell me she loved me in the last and most elemental way she knew how: through cooking?</p>

<p>Obviously I&rsquo;ll never know the answer to that question, but I know how much it hurts in my own life when I plan to cook for my wife and something comes up that prevents that. This way I have of telling the person I love that I love her is thrown off by forces outside my control.</p>

<p>Maybe I really am my mother&rsquo;s son.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/21/cooking/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Nostalgia, Ctd.]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/08/nostalgia/"/>
<updated>2013-04-08T20:58:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/08/nostalgia</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dog issues lead to being chained to home and isolated
Also likely why I am buying Cal gear and listening to the Dead so much
study re: nostalgia being linked to a coping mechanism when we are isolated/alone &ndash; being nostalgic makes us feel happier
<a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2008/10/07/those-were-the-days.html">http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2008/10/07/those-were-the-days.html</a></p>

<p>“Remembrance of things past is not necessarily the remembrance of things as they were.” &ndash; Proust</p>

<p>“We are homesick most for the places we have never known.”
― Carson McCullers</p>

<p>“Memory believes before knowing remembers.</p>

<p>[Light in August]”
― William Faulkner, Light in August</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s strange to think that with a dog and a wife you can feel alone and isolated. Unfortunately all signs are pointing that way for me.</p>

<p>Factors only vaguely under my control have conspired to keep me under stress and limited in my ability to either leave my home (other than for work) or to have people over. That said, after six years here I still have a paltry handful of people I would call friends, many of whom I know are leaving or whose lives have become all-consumed with their children.</p>

<p>I realize that as of late I have been listening to the Grateful Dead quite a bit more than I used to. I also just bought a whole bunch of alma mater branded sports clothes. Not unsurprisingly there is a connection there &ndash; I discovered the Dead my freshman year of college and listen to a lot of it. (My roommate was a huge fan, we both had stereos, and whoever got back to the room first after classes got to choose the music.)</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/08/nostalgia/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Nostalgia]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/07/nostalgia/"/>
<updated>2013-04-07T23:55:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/07/nostalgia</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The desktop image on my computer is that of the final minutes of a sunset on the southern California coast. It was taken a mile or so from where I grew up. Although I have not been back to that place for at least a decade the image still holds me eye every time I see it.</p>

<p>I have always been fascinated by nostalgia. How and why is it that certain times and places always seem to stay with us, seem to come back to us at the strangest times? I may be intrigued by nostalgia, it also makes me nervous. It makes me question where I am in the present. Should I be here? Should I try and recapture something from the past? These are thoughts that come to mind as I get older.</p>

<p>I have recently been reading essays by <a href="http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Didion">Joan Didion</a>. Although she covers a slew of topics, it is often those that relate to her experiences in California that most resonate with me. It was her book of essays <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Slouching-Towards-Bethlehem-Essays-Classics/dp/0374531382/">Slouching Towards Bethlehem</a> which broke down my decades-long personal taboo against underlining/writing in books. The regularity of amazing prose was just too much for me. Normally I will fold up the bottom corner of a page if I want to remind myself that there is a particularly good passage there, but with this book I was folding way too corners to make it practical. So I found a pencil and started underlining.</p>

<p>I think what I connect with most about Didion&rsquo;s writing about California is its strangely dark nostalgia for the place. The ideal of the place mixed with the disintegration that inevitably occurs.</p>

<p>The essays are mostly from the sixties, as she watched the possibilities raised by the counter culture slowly decay and fall apart &ndash; <a href="http://www.potw.org/archive/potw351.html">&ldquo;the center cannot hold.&rdquo;</a> I think though, as someone reading forty-plus years later it also feels like a wise commentary on nostalgia as a whole. The parallel of what could have been (the community spirit of the sixties, etc.) with nostalgia for a believed-to-be better past matched against the parallel of the eventual breakdown of the ideal in action with the reality of that place and time in our past.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8230;California is a place in which a boom mentality and a sense of Chekhovian loss meet in uneasy suspension; in which the mind is troubled by some buried but ineradicable suspicion that things had better work here, because here, beneath that immense bleached sky, is where we run out of continent.</p></blockquote>


<p>It is when Didion focuses on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Ana_winds">Santa Ana winds</a> that plague Los Angeles that I feel the most nostalgic. In the fall and winter these winds come from the east and bring with them fire, violence, and dread.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not that I have particularly fond memories of Santa Ana seasons growing up in Los Angeles, if anything it&rsquo;s just the opposite. I recall days you wished you were outside playing basketball but instead you had to stew inside. Santa Ana season was when the scabbed over wounds in friendships would dry out and crack with the heat, arguments from long ago recurring, long walks home alone though you had made the trek earlier with a friend.</p>

<p>And yet, here I am thinking about them. Maybe it&rsquo;s because of the weather here: it&rsquo;s been a very cold winter and long. Maybe my mind is thinking back to the weather it knows best, the weather of my childhood. Winter has never been my strong suit.</p>

<p>My life has been going through a great number of stresses as of late and another of Didion&rsquo;s passages struck a chord with me:</p>

<blockquote><p>Los Angeles weather is the weather of catastrophe, of apocalypse, and just as the reliably long and bitter winters of New England determine the way life is lived there, so the violence and the unpredictability of the Santa Ana affect the entire quality of life in Los Angeles, accentuate its impermanence, its unreliability. The wind shows us how close to the edge we are.</p></blockquote>


<p>I am someone who tends to be able to deal with the unpredictable, maybe due to my childhood growing up in a land of Santa Anas and earthquakes, things you had no control over and as such could only prepare for and ride out when they came. Maybe it&rsquo;s just a temperament, but as I have grown older I have come to see I can only roll with so many punches before they start being too much for me to handle. When that happens, I return to the things I know. I watch movies I have seen many times already, reread books I have read in the past, listen to the same albums over and over again. The certainty of things I know helps me to weather the stresses of uncertainty.</p>

<p>Maybe this is at the heart of what draws me to Didion&rsquo;s discussion of Santa Anas: these are the uncertainties I know. These are the seemingly random life-stressing events I have experience with and so I become nostalgic for them. I know what to expect during the Santa Anas, but here on a different coast in a different season with parts of my life in constant flux, I am unable to cope. So I look back fondly on things most people would rather avoid.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2013/04/07/nostalgia/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[A final love letter &rarr;]]></title>
<link href="http://www.lettersofnote.com/2012/02/i-love-my-wife-my-wife-is-dead.html"/>
<updated>2012-12-05T22:29:00-05:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/05/a-final-love-letter</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A heartbreaking letter from Dr. Richard Feynman to his late wife. Reminds me I should send more of these to my wife.</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/05/a-final-love-letter/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Journeys End In Lovers Meeting]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/05/journeys-end-in-lovers-meeting/"/>
<updated>2012-12-05T21:42:00-05:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/05/journeys-end-in-lovers-meeting</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently started reading <a href="http://twitter.com/joe_hill">Joe Hill&rsquo;s</a> <a href="http://www.amazon.com/20th-Century-Ghosts-Joe-Hill/dp/B002WTC98S">20th Century Ghosts</a>, a collection of his short stories. The opening tale, <em>Best New Horror</em>, is about a horror fiction editor who goes hunting for a reclusive author and finds more than he was expecting. What inspired me to write this post was the protagonist&rsquo;s use of Shakespeare&rsquo;s line &ldquo;journeys end in lovers meeting.&rdquo; (He thinks it after a day&rsquo;s journey finally leads him to the author&rsquo;s home.) Hill might have just been nodding to Shakespeare, but I think he was actually nodding to another writer, <a href="http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirley_Jackson">Shirley Jackson</a>, and her novel <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Haunting-Hill-House-Shirley-Jackson/dp/0140071083">The Haunting of Hill House</a>, wherein the main character regularly thinks of the same quote.</p>

<p>I finished reading <em>Hill House</em> a week or two ago, so it is still fresh in my memory. Normally books don&rsquo;t stick with me for too long after I finish them. <em>Hill House</em> on the other hand lingered with me for days. Maybe it was because Jackson bookends her novel with the same disconcerting lines:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hill House, not sane, stood by itself against its hills, holding darkness within; it had stood for eighty years and might stand for eighty more. Within, walls continued upright, bricks met neatly, floors were firm, and doors were sensibly shut; silence lay steadily against the wood and stone of Hill House, and whatever walked there, walked alone.</p></blockquote>


<p>The explicit note that Hill House was &ldquo;not sane,&rdquo; contrasted with the list of &ldquo;sane&rdquo; structural details leaves something in you anxious. That anxiety stays with you throughout the book and beyond the final page.</p>

<p>Jackson makes expert use of that anxiety consistently. Nothing is ever directly seen in <em>Hill House</em>, it is all implied or only briefly glimpsed. Loud banging on doors in the night, the sound getting closer and closer, the source of which is never actually faced. The dog heard and briefly glimpsed out the corner of your eye is chased for an hour, but never really seen. If I were speaking about a piece of music, I would say everything was left <a href="http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resolution_(music">unresolved.</a>) As in music, each time something is left unresolved you feel that much more uncomfortable, asking yourself &ldquo;what is going on?&rdquo;<a href="#resolution">[1]</a></p>

<p>This lack of resolution means Jackson never makes it known how much of what the characters experience is in their heads and how much is actually happening. Maybe that is what makes the work so disturbing. It reminds us the line between sanity and madness is a fine one and the slide from the one to the other can be so slow as to be imperceptible. This testing of sanity doesn&rsquo;t only happen to the characters but to you as well. Did that shadow in the corner just get bigger? Is it really you being a klutz that leads you to always stub your toe on the corner of the dresser?</p>

<p>After a few moments thinking this way you laugh it off, but somewhere deep inside the more primitive part of your brain connections are being formed to remember those dangers in the dark, preparing for the worst. I wonder if this isn&rsquo;t one of the reasons we do read horror/suspense fiction and see horror/suspense movies. Maybe there is some evolutionary utility in seeing how things can go wrong for people so that we can make sure we don&rsquo;t make the same mistakes.</p>

<p>Only one of Jackson&rsquo;s characters has any in-depth knowledge of the otherworldly, which doesn&rsquo;t really do him much good anyway. The main character Eleanor definitely doesn&rsquo;t have a horror fiction background:</p>

<blockquote><p>Eleanor knew that, even if her feet would take her as far as the door, her hand would not lift to the doorknob; impartially, remotely, she told herself that no one&#8217;s hand would touch that knob; it&#8217;s not the work hands were made for, she told herself.</p></blockquote>


<p>This is in stark contrast to Hill&rsquo;s protagonist who for most of his professional life has lived and breathed horror stories and as such is ready for the moment when his life becomes one:</p>

<blockquote><p>He hit the front door, banged through it. He didn&#8217;t leap the stairs, but took them one at a time. When you were running from someone, you never jumped the stairs; that was how you twisted an ankle. He had seen it in a hundred horror movies.</p></blockquote>


<p>I think periodic dosed of the macabre might do us some good, like <a href="http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mithridates_VI_of_Pontus#Mithridates.27_antidote">Mithridates</a>. &ldquo;He died <a href="http://www.bartleby.com/123/62.html">old</a>.&rdquo; Reminding us that our time here is short and that even if we live in a much safer world than our ancestors, we should still be weary and look over our shoulder now and again.</p>

<hr>


<br>


<p><a id="resolution">[1]</a>For more on &ldquo;resolution&rdquo; and &ldquo;dissonance&rdquo; and how they affect us I strongly recommend Chapter Six in Jonah Lehrer&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Proust-Was-Neuroscientist-Jonah-Lehrer/dp/B002CMLR5Q">Proust Was A Neuroscientist</a> (even if the author would later go on to make up quotes from Bob Dylan in a later work)</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/05/journeys-end-in-lovers-meeting/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      




<title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving to Octopress]]></title>
<link href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/01/moving-to-octopress/"/>
<updated>2012-12-01T00:44:00-05:00</updated>
<id>http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/01/moving-to-octopress</id>

      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have decided to try out Octopress. Huzzah!</p>
<p><a rel="bookmark" href="http://shanel.github.com/blog/2012/12/01/moving-to-octopress/">&infin; Permalink</a></p>]]></content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
